Oliver Tambo Papers 2000.0144
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Oliver Tambo Papers
undated, 1960-1992.
2000.0144
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
2.0 Linear feet
Oliver Reginald Tambo spent most of his life serving in the struggle against apartheid. During his years in the African National Congress (ANC), Oliver Tambo played a major role in the growth and development of the movement and its policies. He was among the generation of African nationalist leaders who emerged after the Second World War who were instrumental in the transformation of the ANC from a liberal-constitutionalist organisation into a radical national liberation movement.
Tambo, Oliver, 1917-.
Biography
Oliver Reginald Tambo was born in Mbizana in eastern Pondoland in the Cape Province on 27 October 1917. He attended Ludeke Methodist School, and completed his primary education at Holy Cross Mission near Flagstaff. From there he transferred to St. Peter's Secondary School in Johannesburg. After completing his secondary education, Tambo went to the University College of Fort Hare in Alice [South Africa] and earned a Bachelor of Science degree in 1941. He remained at the University of Fort Hare to qualify for an honours degree but was expelled in 1942 during a student strike over demands for a democratically elected student representative council. Following his expulsion he returned to St. Peter's in Johannesburg as a science and mathematics teacher.
In Johannesburg, Tambo became involved with a group of young leaders who advocated a more radical direction for the African National Congress ( ANC). Working with Nelson Mandela, Walter Sisulu, Anton Lembede, Ashby Mda, William Ncomo, C.M. Majombozi, and others, Tambo became a founding member of the ANC Youth League ( ANCYL) in 1944. He served as the Youth League's national secretary and was elected president of the Transvaal in 1948 and national vice-president in 1949.
Tambo moved quickly into a position of influence in the senior ANC and was elected to the Transvaal Executive of the ANC. In 1948, along with Walter Sisulu, he was elected to the National Executive Committee. Tambo was also a member of the committee that drew up the Programme of Action in 1948, which helped move the ANC from a passive organization charged with catering to the elite, to one which mobilized the people for massive campaigns of civil disobedience and non-violent resistance.
Tambo left teaching in 1947 and took up law. With the support of Walter Sisulu he was articled in a Johannesburg law firm. In 1952, he qualified as an attorney, and later that year he established a law practice with Nelson Mandela. Their legal practice championed underprivileged victims of apartheid laws.
Pressure and banning orders from the South Africa n government forced Walter Sisulu to resign from ANC leadership leading to Tambo's appointment as acting secretary-general in 1954. Although banned himself, and restricted to Johannesburg, Tambo was allowed to retain his leadership position in the ANC. During this period he helped to guide the ANC through the Defiance Campaigns and the difficult campaigns against the Western area removal and the introduction of Bantu Education. In December 1956, he was arrested and charged with treason. He was among those discharged from the Treason Trial in late 1957. In 1958, with Albert Luthuli isolated by bans restricting him to his Natal home, Tambo was elected to fill the newly created post of deputy president-general of the ANC. In 1959, Tambo was banned and was forbidden to attend gatherings for five years.
Following the Sharpeville Massacre of 1960, ANC leaders were convinced a banning of the ANC was imminent and made plans for Tambo to leave the country to serve as a foreign spokesman and to establish external missions and mobilize international support against the apartheid system.
From the banning of the ANC and PAC ( Pan Africanist Congress) in 1960 until the unbanning of the ANC in 1990, Tambo led the ANC's organization in exile, living in London, Tanzania, and Zimbabwe. In conjunction with Yusuf Dadoo he was instrumental in the establishment of the South African United Front ( SAUF), which brought together the ANC external missions, the PAC ( Pan Africanist Congress), the South African Indian Congress, and the South West African National Union ( SWANU). Through successful lobbying the SAUF brought about the expulsion of South Africa from the Commonwealth in 1961. Following its initial success the SAUF broke up in July 1961.
Aided by various African governments, Tambo established ANC missions in Egypt, Ghana, Morocco, and London, England. Eventually the ANC operated missions in 27 countries by 1990. Countries hosting missions included all permanent members of the United Nations Security Council with the exception of China.
When the ANC moved to armed struggle and activated Umkhonto we Sizwe, Tambo was instrumental in securing the cooperation of numerous African governments in providing training and facilities for the ANC. Following Albert Luthuli's death in 1967, Tambo was named acting president-general. His appointment was approved by the Morogoro Conference in 1969.
Throughout the 1970s, Tambo's international prestige rose immensely as he traveled the world promoting opposition to the apartheid system. In 1985, Tambo was reelected ANC president at the Kabwe conference. In that role he served as head of the Politico-Military Council (PMC) of the ANC and as commander in chief of Umkhonto we Sizwe.
In 1989, Tambo suffered a stroke and spent several months in Stockholm recuperating. He returned to South Africa in 1991 and was elected national chairperson at the ANC's first legal national conference in July 1991. He was offered the position of chancellor at the University of Fort Hare in 1991. Oliver Tambo died on 24 April 1993.
Scope and Content
The original collection contains correspondence, diaries, notebooks, materials reflecting his changing responsibilities within the ANC and the anti-apartheid struggle, photographs, audio visual materials and ephemera. Researchers shold be aware that descriptions of the contents of folders are intended to highlight significant documents, subjects or individuals and not to provide an inclusive list of materials to be found in the folder. This finding aid describes the microfilm copy of the collection provided by the University of the Witwatersrand.
The Oliver Tambo Papers were arranged at the Department of Historical Papers at the University of the Witwatersrand (Collection ID: A2561) prior to their transfer to the University of Fort Hare. The arrangement of the papers has been retained as it was received from University of the Witwatersrand.
Microfilm rolls correspond to the box numbers as follows:
Roll 1 Boxes 1 - 4
Roll 2 Boxes 4 - 6
Roll 3 Boxes 6 - 12
Roll 4 Boxes 12 - 18
Roll 5 Boxes 28 - 31
Roll 6 Boxes 31 - 35
Roll 7 Boxes 35 - 37
Roll 8 Boxes 37 - 41
Roll 9 Boxes 41 - 44
Roll 10 Boxes 44 - 47
Roll 11 Boxes 47 - 51
Roll 12 Boxes 51 - 54
Roll 13 Boxes 54 - 58
Roll 14 Boxes 58 - 61
Roll 15 Boxes 61 - 67
Roll 16 Boxes 68 - 72
Roll 17 Boxes 73 - 77
Roll 18 Boxes 77 - 81
Roll 19 Boxes 82 - 87
Boxes 19 - 27 and 88 - 95 were not microfilmed.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged in four series: A. Personal Documents, B. Office of the President, C. Special Topics, and D. Press Cuttings. The series structure was arranged in a numerical sequence (i.e., A1=Family, A2 = Finance). The numerical structure is expanded outward to reflect subdivisions (i.e., A1.1= Adelaide Tambo and A1.1.1 represents Adelaide Tambo's correspondence). In many cases the numbering system extends to several places (A12.1.2.1). These same numbers have been annotated on the documents themselves.
Series A: Personal Documents, 1960-1992 includes material relating to Oliver Tambo's family, his health, and travels. Documentation includes correspondence, diaries, notebooks, greeting cards, and get well wishes. The bulk of the material dates from 1960 to 1992. The diaries cover 1980, 1981, and 1990, but are limited in coverage, mainly representing appointments, travel and meetings. Several notable correspondents appear in the correspondence series, including Harry Belafonte, Yusuf Dadoo, Trevor Huddleston, D.F. Malan, Julius Nyerere, Olaf Palme, and Ron Segal. Several transcripts of interviews are also present in this series, as is information on interaction with the media.
Series B. Office of the President, 1960-1990 contains records relating to Tambo's activities as head of the ANC in exile. Records include official correspondence, statements, material on ANC missions, National Executive Committee ( NEC), National Working Committee ( NMC), and information on the various ANC departments and offices. Material on organisations associated with the ANC are also present, and have some overlap with documentation in series C. This series is particularly rich in documentation of the ANC from its banning in 1960 to the subsequent unbanning in 1990. Records reflect efforts to raise international awareness against apartheid policies and are highly illustrative of events in South Africa during this period.
Series C. Special Topics, undated has significant overlap with series B. Records are arranged in five main categories: Conferences, Countries, Individuals, Organisations, and Subjects. The Organisation of African Unity ( OAU) is particularly well documented in the organisations, as are anti-apartheid movements. Within the individuals, Nelson Mandela is well represented.
Series D. Press Cuttings, undated provide strong documentation on general subjects, countries, individuals, and organisations. The finding aid does not include a listing of the press cuttings.
An index of subjects, individuals and organisations follows this finding aid (found at the end of Series C) and is a useful source for finding information on specific topics, events, and people.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to human rights. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
A complete listing of materials associated with the African National Congress and the anti-apartheid movement at the University of Fort Hare is available here.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Custodial History
University of Witwatersrand (Collection ID: A2561) then transferred to the University of Fort Hare.
Alternative Form Available
Original collection is housed and the University of Fort Hare located in Alice, South Africa.
Location of Originals
University of Fort Hare, Alice, South Africa, African National Congress Archives.
Africa-Cultures International Institute.; African National Congress. Archives.; African National Congress.; Artists United Against Apartheid.; Asmal, Kader.; Astor, David.; Belafonte, Harry, 1927-.; Bhutto, Benazir.; Bloom, Anthony, 1914-.; Boesak, Allan Aubrey, 1946-.; Brandt, Willy, 1913-.; British Defence and Aid Fund for Southern Africa.; Buthelezi, Mangosuthu Gatsha.; Carlsson, Ingvar, 1934-.; Castro Ruz, Fidel.; Ceausescu, Nicolae.; Colin, Margaret, 1958-.; Communist Party of India.; Cosby, Bill, 1937-.; Cosby, Camille O. (Camille Olivia), 1944-.; Cunhal, Alvaro.; Davis, Jennifer.; Diouf, Abdon.; Dos Santos, Jose' Eduardo, 1942- or 1946-.; Eriksson, Alison.; Eriksson, Lars-Gunnar.; Ferrari, Frank D.; Frederick, Wayne A.; Genscher, Hans Dietrich.; Goddard, Ruth, 1917-.; Harris, Ann.; Huddleston, Trevor, Bp., 1913-.; International Defence and Aid Fund.; Irish Anti-Apartheid Movement.; Karis, Thomas, 1919-.; King, Coretta Scott, 1927-.; Kleinschmidt, Horst Günter.; Komittee Zuidelijk Afrika.; Lembede, Anton Muziwakhe, 1914-1947.; Lincoln University.; Louw, Raymond.; Luthuli, Albert, 1898-1967.; Machel, Graça.; Majombozi, C.M.; Malan, D.F. (Daniel François), 1874-1959.; Mandela, Nelson, 1918-.; Marchais, Georges, 1920-.; Marin, Manuel.; Mbeki, Govan, 1910-.; Mda, Ashby.; Minty, Abdul S.; Moi, Daniel Arap, 1924-.; Moshoeshoe II, King of Lesotho, 1938-1996.; Mugabe, Robert Gabriel, 1924-.; Mugabe, Sally, 1931-1992.; Nandé', Beyers.; National Union of Seaman (Great Britain).; Ncomo, William.; Nyerere, Julius K. (Julius Kambarage), 1922-.; Omar, Dullah.; Organisation of African Unity.; Pan Africanist Congress.; Pereira, Aristides.; Persson, Carl.; Reddy, E.S.; Robinson, Randall.; Romanov, D.; Sampson, Anthony.; SANSCO.; Segal, Ronald, 1932-.; Shaker, Mohamed Ibrahim.; Sisulu, Walter Max.; Slovo, Joe; Socialist International.; SOMAFCO.; South African Communist Party.; South African Indian Congress.; South African United Front.; South West African National Union.; Soviet Afro-Asian Solidarity Committee.; Stanishev, Dimitur.; Stolenberg, Thorvald.; Tambo, Adelaide.; Tambo, Oliver, 1917-.; Turok, Ben, 1927-.; Umkhonto we Sizwe (South Africa).; University of Fort Hare.; University of the West Indies.; University of the Western Cape.; University of the Witwatersrand.; Uys, Pieter-Dirk.; Vigne, Randolph.; Walters, Ian.; Ware, Helen.; Wilson, Francis.; Yates, Anne Hayden Price, 1939-.; Yusuf Dadoo, 1909-1983.; Zhikov, Todor.; Africa.; Alice, South Africa.; Angola.; Bulgaria.; Egypt.; Germany.; Ghana.; India.; Ireland.; Johannesburg, South Africa.; London, England.; Microfilm.; Morocco.; Nigeria.; People's Republic of Angola.; Poland.; Romania.; South Africa.; Sweden.; Tanzania.; United Kingdom.; Vietnam.; Yugoslavia.; Zimbabwe.
- Series A: Personal Documents, 1960-1993
  - Subseries A1: Family
    - Adelaide Tambo (Box A1., Folder 1)
      - Correspondence from Adelaide Tambo to Oliver Tambo (16 items), 1962, 1969, 1981-1988 (Box A1., Folder 1)
      - Correspondence to Adelaide Tambo (includes two greeting cards, 15 items), 1961-1980 (Box A1., Folder 2)
    - Family/General, (15 items, includes 3 photographs), undated, 1960, 1983, 1985, 1989-1990 (Box A1.1., Folder 2)
    - Greeting Cards/Messages: Birthdays, Christmas etc., includes telexed messages to Oliver Tambo on his 70th Birthday- See also: Greeting Cards/Messags - Birthdays (18 items), undated (Box A1.1., Folder 3)
    - Wedding of Nomatemba (Tembi) Tambo and Martin Kingston, 1981 August 1 (Box A1.1., Folder 4)
      - Correspondence (13 items) Correspondents include: Yusuf and Winnie Dadoo; Trevor Huddleston; N. M. Masemola; Ernst Michanek (Swedish Foreign Ministry); Julius Nyerere and his wife; David Owen (MP) and his wife; Olaf Palme, undated
    - Miscellaneous Personal Matters, (28 items) re to Oliver and Adelaide Tambo Includes: harrassment- handwritten list of threats received against Oliver Tambo on the part of Adelaide; children's education; vehicle registration document ( Adelaide Tambo); ANC Staff Provident Fund ( Oliver Tambo); motor insurance; correspondence re the allocation of land (Wattville) to Oliver Tambo/the purchase of property in Benoni, South Africa by the Tambos, undated, 1960-1992 (Box A1.1., Folder 5)
  - Subseries A2: Finance, 1962-1993
    General note
    Includes correspondence re Oliver Tambo's personal finance affairs; invoices; statements (bank), notices, etc.
    - 1962-1972 (9 items) (Box A2., Folder 1)
    - 1973 (23 items) (Box A2., Folder 2)
      Includes items relating to fire loss at Oliver Tambo's home in North London
    - 1974-1979 (9 items) (Box A2., Folder 3)
    - 1980-1986 (11 items) (Box A2., Folder 4)
    - 1987-1989 (13 items) (Box A2., Folder 5)
    - 1990 (3 items) (Box A2., Folder 6)
    - 1991 (11 items) (Box A2., Folder 7)
      Includes correspondence; bank statements; invoices; final notice
    - 1992-1993 (Box A2., Folder 8)
      Includes bank statements; info on life insurance policies
    - Undated (4 items) (Box A2., Folder 9)
  - Subseries A3: Health, 1975-1991
    - Correspondence (13 items), 1975-1991 (Box A3., Folder 1)
    - Medical Records (24 items), 1978-1991 (Box A3., Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box A3., Folder 3)
      Includes Medical Bills; Prescriptions; Programmes/Exercises; Special Diets
  - Subseries A4: Honourary Degrees/Honourary Membership, 1961-1991
    - Correspondence, (17 items), 1986-1991 (Box A4., Folder 1)
      Corresponents include: National Union of Seamen; Cuban Anti-Apartheid Committee; Lincoln University; University of the West Indies; Africa-Cultures International Institute
  - Subseries A5: Music (61 items), undated
    Includes words of songs (e.g. Song of Africa, Nkosi Sikelel' i-Afrika) and draft music
  - Subseries A6: Public Portraits, (4 items- includes 2 photographs), 1985, 1991
    Correspondents include: Ian Walters (Sculptor); Stanley Uys
  - Subseries A7: Requests, Autographs and Other Information (28 items), undated, 1986-1991
  - Subseries A8: Travel Arrangements (7 items), 1961-1990
    - Subjects include: visa applications; flight bookings; reservation particulars, undated (Box A8., Folder 1)
    - Presidential Visits, Meetings (8 items), 1973-1991 (Box A8., Folder 2)
      Items include: Itinerary: Lars-Gunnar and Alison Eriksson- visit to Africa, 18 April/9 June, 1973; Pamphlet: ANC Leider Tambo in Nederland (Invitation: Komitee Zuidelijk Afrika), 1981; Brief Report on the Presidential Mission to the 18th Congress of the Socialist International, 20 June 1989; Brief Report on the Meeting with Manuel Marin, Vice-President of the EEC (2 July 1989); Brief Report on the Meeting with Raymond Louw (15 May 1991); Handwritten List/Notes ( Oliver Tambo): Invitations; Recommendations for Future Presidential Tours (Travel Arrangements and Accommodation/Scheduling).
  - Subseries A9: Universities, Dealings with...Fort Hare; University of the Western Cape, etc., (See also: Special Topics - Organisations/ University of the Western Cape) (16 items), 1990, 1991, 1992
    Items include: Documents supplied by Wits University re role of Chancellor (sent to Oliver Tambo by Penuell M. Maduna) 25 September 1990; Correspondence between Dullah Omar and Oliver Tambo re graduation, 11/12 October 1990 (2 items); Correspondence: re Oliver Tambo's invitation to become Fort Hare's Chancellor, 21 February 1991; Response from SANSCO re honourary doctorate to be conferred on Oliver Tambo by UDW (March 1991); Facsimiles (2 items) sent by Prof S. Bengu to Oliver Tambo re Chancellorship of Fort Hare (Advertisement) and death of a student in Bisho March (1992).
  - Subseries A10: Personal Documents
    - Cards: Calling/Business Cards, undated (Box A10., Folder 1)
      - Countries (Ambassadors, Ministers) (80 items) (Box A10., Folder 1.1)
      - Individuals (Includes academics) (31 items) (Box A10., Folder 1.2)
      - Media (print and television journalists) (37 items) (Box A10., Folder 1.3)
      - Organisations (45 items) (Box A10., Folder 1.4)
      - United Nations (10 items) (Box A10., Folder 1.5)
      - Miscellaneous (34 items) (Box A10., Folder 1.6)
    - Cards Identity/Membership (15 items), 1980s (Box A10., Folder 2)
      Includes membership card of the June Four Movement; identity cards issued at OAU Assemblies/Summits.
    - Official Documents (7 items), 1970, 1978, 1987 (Box A10., Folder 3)
      Passports (including a Malawian travel document in lieu of a national passport); Driving Licence (Issued March 1970: Lusaka City Council);Firearm Licence (Issued in April 1978: Lusaka City Council); Receipt for Firearm or Ammunition deposited in a Public Warehouse (4 August 1987).
  - Subseries A11: Diaries/Address/Telephone Books/Notebooks/Miscellaneous Notes
    - Diaries (3 items), 1980, 1981, 1990 (Box A11., Folder 1)
    - Address/Telephone Books (4 items and loose transcriptions) (Box A11., Folder 2)
      Includes miscellaneous notes written at random amongst the addresses/numbers.
    - Notebooks/Miscellaneous Loose Leaf Notes, 1970-1989 (Box A11., Folder 3)
      - Miscellaneous Loose Leaf Notes, circa 1971 (Box A11., Folder 3.1)
        Includes "Call for Unity" - PAC.
      - circa 1974 (1 item) (Box A11., Folder 3.2)
      - circa 1977 (1 item) (Box A11., Folder 3.3)
      - circa 1978 (4 items) (Box A11., Folder 3.4)
        Includes Notebook: Visit to Vietnam
      - circa 1979/1980 (3 items) (Box A11., Folder 3.5)
      - circa 1982 (2 items) (Box A11., Folder 3.6)
      - circa 1985 (1 item) (Box A11., Folder 3.6a)
      - 1987 (2 items) (Box A11., Folder 3.7)
      - circa 1988 (4 items) (Box A11., Folder 3.8)
      - circa 1989 (2 items) (Box A11., Folder 3.9)
      - Notebooks: Miscellaneous (11 items), undated (Box A11., Folder 3.1)
        1 item includes telephone numbers/addresses as well as miscellaneous notes
      - Loose Leaf Notes: Miscellaneous (11 files), undated (Box A11., Folder 3.11)
        Includes Reminders/Messages; Notes prepared for Speeches/Statements
      - Draft Minutes/Memoranda (5 items), undated (Box A11., Folder 3.12)
      - Draft Reports/Papers (10 items) (Box A11., Folder 3.13)
      - Early Life (3 items) (Box A11., Folder 3.14)
        Notes explaining the origin of Oliver Tambo's letters to Joyce and Ruth Goddard (1928-1940). Includes excerpts from letters to both received from and referring to Oliver Tambo. 7p. Ts. Handwritten notes ( Oliver Tambo) re life at St Peters/admission to Fort Hare. 3p. Notebook: Dictated to Speech Therapist, 5 September 1989.
      - Draft/Unfinished Letters (14 items), undated (Box A11., Folder 3.15)
      - Biographical Details (5 items), undated (Box A11., Folder 3.16)
  - Subseries A12: Greeting Cards/Messages, 1983-1990
    - Birthdays (Box A12., Folder 1)
      - General (24 items), 1989 (Box A12., Folder 1.1)
        Includes written list of telephone messages, 27 October 1989. Correspondents include: ANC Department of Education; ANC Department of Information and Publicity; ANC Headquarters Staff; ANC members - United Kingdom and Ireland; ANC National Youth Committee; High Commissioner for Tanzania, Mrs. Malecela and Staff.
      - Oliver Tambo's 70th Birthday, 1987 October 27 (Box A12., Folder 1.2)
        - ANC (40 items), undated (Box A12., Folder 1.2.1)
          Correspondents include: ANC membership - Angola; Angola - leadership of the Security Department; Department of Finance; Department of Transport; International Headquarters; Quibaxe Centre Youth Committee; Quibaxe - Women's Section; SOMAFCO Student-body; UmKonto we Sizwe; Viena Transit Camp. Publication: Issued by ANC: A 70th Birthday Tribute, (see also: ANC Publications)
        - Countries (22 items), undated (Box A12., Folder 1.2.2)
          Includes list of greetings/messages. Ts. Correspondents include: People's Republic of Angola; Ebrahim Babaginda ( Nigeria); Nicolae Ceausescu; Communist Party of India; Hans-Dietrich Genscher ( Germany); Carl Persson (Ambassador: Sweden); D. Romanov (Ambassador: Bulgaria); Fidel Castro Ruz; Tanzania High Commission; Jelko Zagar (Ambassador: Yugoslavia).
        - Individuals (27 items), undated (Box A12., Folder 1.2.3)
          Correspondents include: Harry and Julie Belafonte; Frank Ferrari; Trevor Huddleston; Lisbet Palme; Randall Robinson; E. S. Reddy; Joe Slovo.
        - Organisations (43 items), undated (Box A12., Folder 1.2.4)